A Guide to the Records of the Governor's Office, Executive Mansion, 2002-2006
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Governor's Office, Executive Mansion, 2002-2006
The Library of Virginia
42419
1.58 cu. ft. (5 boxes)
Virginia. Governor's Office. Executive Mansion.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Margaret Hughson, Office of the Governor, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, accession 42419, transferred on 18 January 2006 and accessioned 19 January 2006.
Historical Information
Virginia's Executive Mansion has been home, office and center of official entertaining for governors and their families since 1813. It was the second governor's residence constructed in the nation, and is today the oldest governor's residence still used for its original purpose.
The Executive Mansion was Virginia's third state-owned governor's residence. The first two governors under the Constitution of 1776, Patrick Henry and Thomas Jefferson, occupied the colonial Governor's Palace in Williamsburg. In the spring of 1780, Governor Jefferson moved with the government to the new capital in Richmond. For a short period after that relocation, Virginia's governors occupied rental properties.
During the latter part of the 18th century, a second governor's residence was built in Richmond, on almost the same spot the Mansion stands today. The building, a modest frame structure, stood for twelve gubernatorial administrations and was home to three future United States presidents - James Monroe as governor, and John Tyler, Jr. and William Henry Harrison while their fathers were governors.
n 1811, Governor John Tyler, Sr., arguing before the Legislature that the house was "intolerable for a private family," brought about the decision to build the current residence. Under James Monroe's direction and as his last act as Governor, the General Assembly directed "the building of a house for the use of the governor of the commonwealth, on the lot on which the present governor's house stands."
Almost two-hundred years later, with gratitude to Tyler and Monroe, the Mansion remains in the middle of the City. During its long history, the Executive Mansion has been home to 54 Governors and continues to serve not only as a residence to the Chief Executive of Virginia, but also as a place for official state business. There have been 2 major interior renovations (Swanson and Gilmore Administration) and one exterior renovation (Baliles administration) over the long history of the Mansion. The Mansion has seen many famous people and VIPs walk through the mansion, the first floor was almost destroyed by fire, numerous stories of the ghost have been shared over the years, and even hosted three funeral viewings. Families, the children, and their pets have come and gone, but the history that lives within the walls of the Mansion is rich and all who walk through the doors contribute to the legacy of the oldest continually occupied Governor's residence in the United States.
-Taken from Virginia's Executive Mansion Web Site
Scope and Content
The Governor's Office, Executive Mansion records are housed in 5 boxes. This collection documents gifts received by Governor Mark R. Warner (2002-2006), correspondence of the Mansion Director and functions held at the Executive Mansion during his term.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Gift Files
Series II. Mansion Director's Files
Series III. Mansion Events
Related Material
Web site of First Lady Lisa Collis, 2005-2006 part of the Virginia's Political Landscape, Fall 2005, Web collection.
Contents List
- Series I. Gift Files, 2002-2005., Extent: 0.35 cu.ft. (1 box).
  This series consists of gift acknowledgements from Governor Mark R. Warner. The correspondence are arranged as follows: 2004-2005 and first letter of surname, 2002-2003 and first letter of surname, and by date. Also included is a list of gifts received, arranged annually, for the Governor's Statement of Economic Interest. The list includes the name and address of the gift giver, type of gift and approximate value.
  - 2004-2005
    - A-D (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - F-M (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - N-W (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 2002-2003
    - A-G (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - H-Z (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - January 2002-June 2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - July 2003-December 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - List of Gifts Received, 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II. Mansion Director's Files, 2002-2006., Extent: 0.18 cu.ft. (1 box).
  This series documents the activities and correspondence of the Mansion Director (Bruce Garrison and Amy Bridge). Also included are invitation lists that were not entered into the Office of the Governor's constituent correspondence tracking database.
  - Bruce Garrison Correspondence, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Amy Bridge Correspondence, 2002-2005 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Invitation Lists, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series III. Mansion Events, 2002-2005., Extent: 1.05 cu.ft. (3 boxes).
  This series documents functions held at the Executive Mansion during the term of Governor Mark R. Warner (2002-2006). Arranged by date of event, the files contain invitations, invitation lists, event logistics, menus and schedule. Most events only contain invitation/RSVP lists.
  - Inaugural Luncheon, 2002 January 12. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - New Legislator's Reception, 2002 January 17. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Boehringer Ingelheim Luncheon, 2002 January 18. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - College Presidents' Meeting, 2002 February 7. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Docent's Tea, 2002 February 14. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Legislative Reception, 2002 February 20. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Pages' Reception, 2002 February 21. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Legislative Reception, 2002 February 28. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - State Council of Higher Education Luncheon, 2002 March 1. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - IHO Patrick O'Connell, 2002 March 2. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Congressional Delegation Luncheon, 2002 March 18. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Reception, 2002 July 8. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - VEI Luncheon, 2002 July 12. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Reception, 2002 July 17. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Reception, 2002 August 6. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - PASS Recption, 2002 August 7. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - PASS Reception, 2002 August 28. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - VGEA Reception, 2002 September 3. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Dinner for Chinese Ambassador, 2002 September 9. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Preservation Alliance of Virginia Reception, 2002 September 22. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - VMAC Reception, 2002 October 8. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Reception, 2002 October 17. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Larry Sabato 50th Reception, 2002 October 21. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Literacy Coffee, 2002 October 30. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Reception, 2002 November 25. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Reception, 2002 December 5. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Southern Technology Dinner, 2002 December 10. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Education Luncheon, 2002 December 11. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Virginia School Superintendents Reception, 2003 January 13. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Meeting, 2002 January 14. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - SCHEV Luncheon, 2003 January 16. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - PASS Business Reception, 2003 January 16. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Travel South Conference Bid Luncheon, 2003 January 23. (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Pages Reception, 2003 January 30. (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Legislative Receptions, 2003 February 11 and 12. (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - UNOS Reception, 2003 March 18. (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Virginia Congressional Delegation Meeting, 2003 March 31. (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - VFMA Coffee and Va. Health Care Foundation's Heroes in Health Care Event, 2003 April 30 and 2003 May 6. (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Agency Head Meeting, 2003 May 5. (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Public Service Awards, 2003 May 7. (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Virginia Wine Awards, 2003 June 2. (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - PASS Reception, 2003 June 9. (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Jet Blue Luncheon, 2003 June 26. (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Ask Why Press Conference, 2003 June 30. (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - VEI Luncheon, 2003 July 11. (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Governor's Fellows Reception, 2003 July 22. (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Governor's Fellows Luncheon, 2003 July 25. (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Forbes CEO Dinner, 2003 October 3. (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Israeli Ambassador Luncheon, 2003 October 7. (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Reception, 2003 October 7. (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Math Science Awards Reception, 2003 October 13. (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - VEI Luncheon, 2003 October 31. (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - ECS Reception and ECS Breakfast, 2003 November 12 and 14. (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - ECS Breakfast, 2003 November 14. (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Higher Education Reception, 2003 November 19. (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Tax Tribute Ceremony, 2003 November 26. (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Tree Lighting, 2003 December 5. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Holiday Open House, 2003 December 6-7. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Press Corps Reception, 2003 December 9. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - SGA Breakfast, 2003 December 10. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - VEDP Reception, 2003 December 10. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - VITA Leadership Breakfast, 2003 December 11. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Events, 2004 January. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - DoE-DPB Reception, 2004 January 6. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - School Superintendent Reception, 2004 January 20. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - New Legislator Reception, 2004 January 22. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Legislative Aides Reception, 2004 January 29. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Events, 2004 February. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Pages' Reception, 2004 February 25. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Spouses Luncheon, 2004 February 27. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Governor's High School Leadership Reception, 2004 March 8. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Congressional Delegation Meeting, 2004 March 29. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Employee Awards Luncheon, 2004 May 5. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Agency Head Reception, 2004 May 10. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Governor's Wine Awards Reception, 2004 June 1. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Governor's Fellows Reception, 2004 June 22. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Governor's Fellows Luncheon, 2004 July 22. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Tour for Romanian Dignitaries, 2004 July 29. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Virginia Lottery Reception, 2004 September 16. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Chamber Reception, 2004 October 18. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Chesapeake Bay Reception, 2004 November 11. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - General Assembly Leadership Dinner, 2004 November 16. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Community College Reception, 2004 November 22. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - American Indian Tax Tribute Ceremony, 2004 November 24. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Press Reception, 2004 December 6. (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Agency Head Reception, 2004 December 20. (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Capitol Police Reception, 2004 December 21. (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - State of the Commonwealth Reception, 2005 January 12. (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Virginia School Superintendents Reception, 2005 January 18. (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - JMU Football Reception, 2005 January 24. (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Legislative Aide Reception, 2005 January 31. (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - House of Delegates Reception, 2005 February 2. (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Senate Reception, 2005 February 3. (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Transportation Reception, 2005 February 9. (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Higher Education Reception, 2005 February 10. (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Pages' Reception, 2005 February 14. (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - NARFE/AARP Reception, 2005 February 15. (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Community College Luncheon, 2005 February 17. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Spouses Coffee, 2005 February 25. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Congressional Delegation Meeting, 2005 March 14. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - India Dinner, 2005 March 22. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - John Marshall 250th Birthday Luncheon, 2005 April 30. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - VMFA Dinner, 2005 May 16. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Veteran's Reception, 2005 June 8. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Governor's Cup Wine Awards, 2005 June 13. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Governor's Fellows Reception, 2005 July 7. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Governor's Fellows Luncheon, 2005 July 29. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Counselor Breakfast, 2005 August 25. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - NASCAR Lunch, 2005 August 23. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - COVITS Reception, 2005 September 18. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - VentureSouth Reception, 2005 October 5. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Finance Building Dedication, 2005 October 28. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Literacy Foundation Reception, 2005 November 1. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Tax Tribute, 2005 November 23. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Jamestown Reception, 2005 December 1. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Education Initiatives Reception, 2005 December 1. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Education Recap, 2005 December 5. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Education Reception, 2005 December 5. (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Press Reception, 2005 December 13. (Box 5, Folder 22)